Finding Aid for Richard W. Bailey papers, 1972-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard W. Bailey papers 1972-2008
Bailey, Richard W.
4 linear feet
8513 Aa 2
Professor of English at the University of Michigan, trustee of Washtenaw Community College, and Democratic Party worker. Correspondence, newsletters, leaflets and reports concerning Democratic politics at the state and local levels, platform hearings for the 1976 National Democratic platform; also papers relating to his activities with St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church, and Genesis of Ann Arbor.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Richard W. Bailey (donor no. 5893 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Richard W. Bailey was born October 26, 1939 in Pontiac, Michigan. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Connecticut in 1965. He was appointed assistant professor of English at the University of Michigan in 1965. He became associate professor in 1971 and full professor in 1976. Along with several other honors, he was named Fred Newton Scott Collegiate Professor of English. Much of his research, as well as the classes he taught, were on such topics as linguistics, slang, and poetry. He is the author of many books including Nineteenth-Century English, Images of English: A Cultural History of the Language and Rogue Scholar.
In addition to his academic career, Bailey has served as trustee of Washtenaw Community College in Ann Arbor, Michigan. In 1976, he was a member of the platform committee of the National Democratic Convention. He has also been senior warden of St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church in Ann Arbor.
The Richard W. Bailey Papers consist of four series: Democratic Party Politics, Episcopal Church Activities, Course Materials, and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Bailey, Richard W.; Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Genesis Corporation (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. Dept. of English.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Democratic Party Politics 1973-1978
  The Democratic Party Politics series (2 linear feet) documents meetings of various Democratic groups in Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County between 1973 and 1978. There is also material from his work on the platform committee of the National Democratic Convention in 1976.
  - Ann Arbor politics 1973-1976, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County and Second Congressional District Democratic meetings 1973-1978, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan politics and Democratic State Central Committee 1973-1976, 18 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan Democratic Party platform committee, foreign policy subcommittee 1973-1976, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - National Democratic Party platform committee hearings 1976 (Box 2)
- Episcopal Church activities 1973-1991
  The Episcopal Church Activities series (1 linear foot) comprises records pertaining to the local Episcopal Church community in Ann Arbor from 1973 through 1991. Included in this series are records of the founding of Genesis of Ann Arbor, a partnership between St. Clare's Episcopal Church and Temple Beth Emeth, a Reform Jewish congregation, which formally established co-ownership of a common sanctuary in 1975.
  - Episcopal Student Foundation undated, 1973-1981, 8 folders (Box 3)
    (includes Canterbury House, later Canterbury Loft)
  - St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church 1976-1991, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Episcopal Church, Diocese of Michigan 1978-1983, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Genesis of Ann Arbor 1980s, 1 volumes; 3 folders (Box 3)
    (corporation governing the facilities used jointly by St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church and Temple Beth Emeth)
- Course Materials 1969-2008
  The Course Materials series (0.8 linear feet) holds a number of Bailey's syllabi, hand-outs, assignments, exams, course readings, and class notes from his time teaching at the University of Michigan. These files are organized by year and then course number.
  - English 409, Winter 1969 (Box 4)
  - English 407, Fall 1969 (Box 4)
  - English 307, Term III-A 1972 (Box 4)
  - English 307, Fall 1972 (Box 4)
  - English 536/Linguistics 661, Fall 1972 (Box 4)
  - English 536/Linguistics 661, Term III-B 1973 (Box 4)
  - English 409, Fall 1974 (Box 4)
  - Composition/Literature 631/Slavic 486, Fall 1974 (Box 4)
  - Composition/Literature 631, Fall 1975 (Box 4)
  - English 603, Fall 1975 (Box 4)
  - English 409, Winter 1981 (Box 4)
  - English 305, Fall 1995 (Box 4)
  - English 140, Winter 1996 (Box 4)
  - English 309, Winter 1996 (Box 4)
  - English 239, Fall 1996 (Box 4)
  - English 506, Fall 1996 (Box 4)
  - English 308, Winter 1997 (Box 4)
  - English 239, Winter 1998 (Box 4)
  - English 309, Winter 1998 (Box 4)
  - English 305, Fall 1998 (Box 4)
  - English 240, Winter 1999 (Box 4)
  - English 309, Winter 1999 (Box 4)
  - English 506, Fall 1999 (Box 4)
  - English 240, Fall 2000 (Box 4)
  - English 305, Fall 2000 (Box 4)
  - English 308, Winter 2001 (Box 4)
  - English 506, Winter 2001 (Box 4)
  - English 305, Fall 2002 (Box 4)
  - English 309, Fall 2002 (Box 4)
  - English 802, Fall 2002 (Box 4)
  - English 239, Winter 2003 (Box 4)
  - English 309, Winter 2003 (Box 4)
  - English 305, Winter 2004 (Box 4)
  - English 506, Winter 2004, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - English 317, Fall 2004 (Box 4)
  - English 305, Winter 2005 (Box 4)
  - English 309, Winter 2005 (Box 4)
  - English 305, Winter 2006 (Box 4)
  - English 309, Winter 2006 (Box 4)
  - English 406, Winter 2006 (Box 4)
  - English 229, Winter 2008 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Legal Consulting (Box 4)
  - Writings and Reviews (Box 4)